Very occasionally in the music business,
an artist arrives and you can't believe
he or she is real. They are so good,
they seem to be flawless. And Michael
Jackson was one of those.
>> He changed the face of music, the sound
of music, and the industry.
>> Michael's work was able to cross
divisions. uh and and reach people all
over the world.
>> Everyone wanted to be like Michael
Jackson. Dress like him, sing like him,
do the moonwalk, put the glove on the
hand. I mean, we all wanted to be him
because he was an enigma. We just
couldn't understand how he could do all
these things. It was almost like he
wasn't human.
>> There was a media caricature, Michael
Jackson, which is a very kind of
simplified version of him. And then
there's Michael Jackson, the artist, who
to me is a lot more interesting.
There are very few artists who have
obsessed the world like Michael Jackson
did. Now musical royalty, his singles
topped the charts all over the globe,
selling over 350 million records whilst
holding the record for the bestselling
album of all time. This documentary will
cover all aspects of his life from the
Jackson 5 to This Is It.
This is it. I mean, this is really it.
This is the final. This is the final
curtain call.
>> Join us as we remember the king.
>> So, Michael Jackson was born in August
1958. Eight brothers and sisters. Gary,
Indiana, a community where the majority
of the population was steeltown workers.
a part of the country as well that was
suffering from high unemployment. His
dad, Joseph Jackson, this strict
disciplinarian, we all know that, a
steel town worker, but also a musician
himself in a band called the Falcons.
His mother, Catherine, uh an adoring
mom, bringing up all these kids.
>> Michael Jackson's uh past is is a
difficult one. It's a complex one. He's
the kind of quintessential child star
who's kind of pushed into the business
into show business at a very early age.
The strict regime imposed on him by his
father, Joseph Jackson, meant that he
was working night and day. I mean, the
background for the Jackson family was
very, very modest. Joe Jackson, who
managed the band and was also the father
in the family, was always very very
certain that he was going to turn his
children into stars. I think it was
probably pretty disturbing to him in
many ways that Michael was the brother
who very clearly was the most talented
because he was never particularly close
to Michael and he always probably gave
Michael the harshest treatment.
his father uh was abusive uh both
emotionally and physically.
>> The impact I think that Joe's strictness
had on him was very very very
disturbing.
>> Michael himself
talked of the horror of uh being beaten
by his father. Whipped was the word and
how his father would sit there as they
were rehearsing with a belt waiting to
smack them if they got it wrong. You
know, people respond to that kind of
abuse differently. And with some of the
other brothers, I think that, you know,
it didn't impact them the same way
psychologically that it did Michael. You
have to discern your children. You have
to know which children can take certain
uh disciplines and which can't that you
have to sometimes maneuver with certain
kids and treat them a little bit
different, get the point across, but
maybe do it a different way so that they
can handle it. Um, I don't think that
Joe ever did that with Michael. He's a
very sensitive person. So in other
words, when he would chastise the other
brothers and the other siblings, they
managed to handle that intensess from
the father. But Michael, it had a
different effect. He was very sensitive.
It really hurt him and he he carried it
throughout the rest of his life. You
know that his father drove him and
pushed him but never treated him like a
son. In fact, they called him Joseph.
They didn't call him dad or daddy or
father. His name was Joseph. And so it
kind of represented that emotional
detachment. Every time he would speak
about his father, his face would
contort. You could see that he was
really, really stressed about his
experience with his father.
Michael has said that there were, you
know, there was a sense of joy in these
early years, you know, sometimes in the
hotels they'd have pillow fights and
things like that. But when he reflects
on his early years, in spite of the
exuberance that you hear coming out of
those records, he was sad and he was
lonely. What Michael learned very early
on in his life was that music and the
stage was the place where he felt most
at home.
>> There was a reason why he was winning
talent shows at the age of eight in the
community while he transferred with his
family to Los Angeles in 1969 because
the kid had ridiculous talent. But of
course, he was part of a group, the
Jackson 5, formed by Father Joe, picked
up by Mottown Records, and the rest is
history.
The Jackson 5, the first black boy band,
consisted of Michael, Maron, Jackie,
Tito, and Jeremy, who formed the band in
1962.
At first, their father Joseph did not
approve, but later decided to manage the
band, who initially struggled to get
noticed.
Glattis Knight was the first Mottown
artist to bring the Jacksons to the
attention of Barry Gordy. She had
witnessed them win the Apollo talent
show at the Apollo Theater in New York.
However, Barry didn't act at that time.
Then a minor artist named Bobby Taylor
really thought these guys have to be on
Mottown. and he
really pressured the company and
arranged for them to have a
demonstration video made.
And uh when this was shown to Barry
Gordy, he changed his mind.
>> The Jackson 5 were part of this Mottown
sound which was fresh. It was uh for
young America. It was supposed to have
kind of a crossover appeal. And with the
Jackson 5, you know, they came towards
the tail end uh of the Mottown era. Uh,
and they were kind of the first boy band
and kind of established that kind of new
music that could appeal to young people,
that could appeal to black and white.
And I think that that that was kind of
the new niche that the Jackson 5 fil.
Barry Gordy said that the first Jackson
5 singles would be written by the
corporation. No names, just the
corporation who were actually four
people. He was one of them. Freddy
Perin, Dee Richards, Alonso Meiselle,
and Barry Gory said, "We're going to
have three number ones with the first
three singles." That was the goal. Very
audacious, of course. But with this
tremendous songwriting talent, they
succeeded. Think I Want You Back was the
first time that the Jackson 5 really
worked as a pop packet. I Want You Back
is just the classic pop song. Uh, you
know, just bursts right out of the
speakers. When you put the needle down
on I Want You Back, which I did when I
was at my college radio station in 1969,
you were floored.
First of all, the thrilling piano
gassando at the beginning
and then that whailing melisma from
Michael.
>> And then he lands on the first word when
>> I want you around.
>> And he had us at the first word. we
already were owned by this extraordinary
young talent.
>> Everybody was just fanatical about them.
I think the package of the Jackson 5
worked so well is because obviously
Michael Jackson was this huge talent,
but he was incredibly young. But I think
the feeling was because it was a family
band and he was spending all his time
with his brothers who were part of this
group that there wasn't exploitation of
any form because it almost felt as if
we're comfortable with this because
we're part of a family. And that was
very much how they were sold and and
promoted as a family band. It is rather
strange seeing a bunch of young people
uh carrying on with the professionalism
of an older dance troop,
but they could do that. And it was
obvious that uh Joe, the father, had
instilled in them the necessity to be
visually as well as musically appealing.
>> The thing with the Jacksons was when you
saw them on TV, you would run
downstairs. whoever was in the house,
everyone was just run downstairs, go
straight to the TV, and be glued to it.
And that's what the whole world was like
when they saw them because first of all,
there these young kids, they're
extremely talented. They're dancing.
They're doing everything. And then this
little boy comes in front and has this
voice that just you're like, how in
God's name can he sing like that? So
then you've got the kids like me at that
time, 6 years old, wishing they could be
like him. And then you've got the
grown-ups wishing that they could do the
dance moves. And Michael's voice
captivated you.
>> Michael was so talented that immediately
once Joe Jackson started training them
and started rehearsing with them and
started, you know, putting them in these
contests, it became apparent that
Michael Jackson was a star.
Although it was clear Michael was the
most talented of his siblings, it is
also not surprising he decided to embark
on a solo career as he was the most
damaged by how dysfunctional the family
were in the early years largely due to
their father.
But it was really when he made this move
that he truly took the spotlight as his
era's most influential artist.
>> His voice was superior to the others. He
was the one you were obsessed with cuz
he had this cute little face.
>> Beyond Michael Jackson's talent, what
made him kind of go beyond the group was
his ambition. You know, he was a student
of the craft. And so when it was time
for him to branch out on his own, he had
a lot of ideas of what he wanted to do.
>> So Michael Jackson in 1979 brings out
Offthe-Wall, in my opinion, his greatest
solo record.
95.
>> Off the Wall was Michael's first solo
album. Uh, at the time he was still
making albums with his brothers, but
this was a chance for him to say, "Okay,
I've had all these ideas building up,
watched some of the best artists at
Mottown, and now it was his chance to
write his own songs, you know, to help
produce his own songs." And so with
Offthe-Wall, he teamed up with the
legendary Quincy Jones.
>> The most important thing about Quincy
Jones meeting Michael Jackson, I
believe, was that you had the older
head, the experienced musician, and I
mean real musician meeting this
protetéé. And then obviously, you know,
this is why I think everything exploded
after that because there was definitely
a next level that they went to when
Michael collaborated with Quincy Jones.
>> You know, Quincy Jones came also to the
project with this incredible background.
And Michael liked that. Michael liked
that versatility because he didn't want
to do the same stuff that he'd been
doing with his brothers. He wanted to
kind of create a new sound. And uh you
know with off the wall that's what they
accomplished.
without that chemistry, synergy, and
relationship with producer Quincy Jones
that was formed on the set of The Whiz,
the movie he did with Diana Ross,
produced by Quincy Jones in 1977.
Without that moment, we wouldn't have
1979 Epic Records, Michael Jackson's
first solo album. Girl, close your eyes.
>> The album Off the Wall was Jackson's
first step to becoming the king of pop,
he was establishing himself as the most
diverse musical artist the world had
ever seen. with iconic dance moves and
an abundance of number one singles.
>> He also won his first Grammy for best
R&B vocal performance with Don't Stop
Till You Get Enough.
>> Don't Stop Till You Get Enough was such
a significant moment in the development
of Michael Jackson as a superstar.
It came at the time when disco was
starting to fizzle out and of course it
really helped strengthen Michael's
identity of not only a performer and
songwriter but also a dancer and that's
what we got to see in the video.
They listen to the demos of that song
and it's just amazing the the kind of
craft craftsmanship, you know, at that
young age that he already, you know,
from watching other people uh just had
this kind of natural sense of rhythm and
then you add on to that Quincy Jones
incredible production where he brings in
all of these kind of studio veterans and
it's just layers and layers of sound and
it's just incredible.
of my life.
Damnision.
>> I mean, this guy was forward thinking
and there's a reason why he gave us
Thriller some seven years later. Well,
if Michael Jackson was a superstar
before the release of Thriller, as soon
as Thriller released, he almost
instantly transformed into a mega star.
Now, I've often referred to Thriller as
the album that ruined the record
business because even though it is an
all-time great classic and is the
all-time bestseller, of course, almost
no other album comes up to it in terms
of quality of tracks. Thriller, I think
by most people's reckoning, will always
be regarded as Michael Jackson's
creative peak. What he did is surprise
everyone by releasing as the first
single from the album a duet with Paul
McCartney, The Girl is Mine, which was a
bit of a soft mid-tempo ballad. Two
great iconic stars in one record. It
didn't set the world on fire. We were
waiting for the big sizzle and it came
with the release of Billy Jean and he
never looked back.
Billy Jean, a massive song that's had
huge impact and continues to have huge
impact. The huge talents of Quincy
Jones, who co-produced and co-wrote the
track, were obviously very visible. And
the lyrical content Michael always said
was in reference to the groupies that he
and his brother encountered while they
were members of the Jackson 5. People
were crazy about the Jackson 5 and
Michael Jackson. So I think he was
really surprised that people would react
like that. You know, girls would would
would want to have his children and he
was still a kid. I think Billy Jean was
um speaking about how certain fans would
pretty much sort of pretend that they
were having his children.
>> And it's such an interesting song
because it became this big hit with a
very unusual theme, darker song. It's a
song about distrust and anxiety and
paranoia. And you know, Michael was
beginning to write songs that that maybe
got people to dance still, but also that
were exploring some of the things that
he was experiencing.
>> It's a historic hit for a variety of
reasons. One is it forced
MTV to play videos by black artists. CBS
at the time said, "If you don't put
Billy Gene on, you're not getting our
videos." Because Billy Jean was such a
big hit,
the public loved it and wanted it and
MTV had to recant.
And ever since then, of course, there
have been black artists on MTV.
>> Just when you watch the Billy Jean
video, there's this kind of mystery
about it. you know, it's kind of like
this post-modern wasteland, you know,
and there's this paparazzi that's
stalking Michael and, you know, he's
disappearing under bed sheets and
there's this kind of narrative flow to
it, but at the same time, when you get
to the end of the music video, there's a
lot of questions, but just the
atmosphere is so mysterious. The Billy
Jean video uh had a great impact
because, first of all, the production
values, they're not expensive, were were
riveting. the the lit paving stones
which would light up as Michael passed
them were very eye-catching
>> the technology and the sophistication of
the video in that time when we were
still just coming out of uh black and
white TVs you know and it was like woo
this is amazing
>> but it didn't all go to plan only a
certain number of the pavement squares
themselves could and would light up once
Michael's foot touched them. So, Michael
had a small matter of seconds, something
like 20 seconds to learn the sequence as
to which uh pavement slabs would light
up once his foot touched them. Director
said, "Michael, are you going to be okay
with this? I'm so sorry." Because the
original plan was that every single slab
would illuminate. It was going to be a
magical moment. Michael just did his
thing. He looked at the director said,
"Hey, I can do this." And off he went.
He did it in one take.
Don't get advice.
>> He completely brought the house down and
won an Emmy award for his performance of
Billy Jean at the Mottown 25 anniversary
special and he moonwalked. Now he'd been
taught the moonwalk by Jeffrey Daniels
of the group Shalomar. Michael Jackson
had an incredible sense of showmanship
and uh it it took his career to another
level.
Now, no one realized that the single
release of Thriller itself was coming.
The thriller song was actually one of
the later songs for the album. Michael
had written a bunch of songs. Uh, and
one of the songwriters that that had
worked on Off the Wall was also working
on Thriller, his name was Rod Temperton,
and he was writing a bunch of songs and
one of them was called Starlight. And he
presented that to Michael and to Quincy,
and they liked it a lot. They changed
the title from Starlight to Thriller.
Try to get just a title that would kind
of match the tone of some of the songs
that Michael was bringing in.
People could not believe
that this song was what it was.
Everybody was obsessed. You're walking
down the street. Everyone was dressing
like Michael Jackson. Everyone had the
same clothes on. I mean, we're talking
everyone was Thriller. Everyone became
Michael Jackson. That's how big a
phenomena it was.
>> And until the music video premiered on
music television channels around the
world, MTV, Channel 4 in the UK, well,
until that moment, Michael was at this
level. The album Thriller was here,
hovering the stratosphere. Once Thriller
was released, once the world saw that
video, he went into orbit and he never
looked back.
>> When that video came on TV,
>> you didn't do anything. You didn't make
a cup of tea. You didn't speak to
anyone. You know, this is the first
video that was like a movie. It was I
mean, it was a movie. you know, you were
just like, "Wow, you've never seen an
artist, performer, singer make a video
that's like a movie." It was a
phenomenon.
>> Thriller is unlike anything people have
seen before because it's basically, it's
not a music video. It's a short film.
>> There are two elements of Thriller which
are
unforgettable. One is the transformation
of Michael from this nice guy bringing
the girl home and then suddenly the eyes
light up and
he turns into this creature
and then the zombies rise and there's
the dance of the zombies. That
fascination with the zombies continues
to this day in popular entertainment. I
mean, it's been in feature films. It's
been on TV, but an absolute classic
video.
>> It's 30 minutes long. It's one of the
biggests selling music videos of all
time, and it's the greatest video of all
time.
He was now a veteran performer whose
music and choreography had encapsulated
the world who were on tent hooks
awaiting his third solo album, Bad.
>> It was interesting in 1987 when Michael
released the Bad album. People weren't
just talking about the music. They were
also talking about the fact that he
might have been trying to reach out to a
generation that was starting to really
embrace hip-hop music and that was
becoming a huge cultural musical force
in the industry. However, they were also
talking about the look, Michael's look
and the artwork, the front cover. In
fact, the picture chosen for the bad
album, Michael looking a bit more
street, a bit more gangster.
>> Michael's self-image has changed
with Offthe-Wall.
He wanted to make an important hit
album. After Offthe-wall had had great
success, but had won two Grammy Awards
in R&B categories only. He felt the work
underrecognized
and was hungry for mass acceptance
across the pop world. He achieved that
with Thriller. So now he's done that
professionally and he's beginning to
worry about his personal image.
And so he poses on the sleeve of bad
looking like a tough guy.
So what he wanted to do was take more
control of his image. He had a much
harder image at that time.
>> It was a huge change for everyone. We
couldn't believe his image had changed
that much. I mean it he looked like a
little bit rock star now. Even though
you, you know, Thriller had some edgier
parts to it, there was still this sense
that Michael was like a Peter Pan
character,
>> but now you think, well, you know, he's
as talented as ever, but he's he's
worried about how he's coming across.
>> Michael wanted to come out with a song
that was a little bit edgier. And the
title track, Bad, was actually intended
as a duet with Prince. Uh, and they met
and discussed it. Prince really liked it
and Prince said it'd be a number one
hit, but he felt like it was set up for
Michael to win. Uh, you know, because
they were going to do this big music
video where they're kind of having a
dance off and, you know, all this kind
of drama to it. Uh, you know, the two
kind of big pop icons of the decade. So,
Prince backed out and Michael ended up
doing it as a solo. At the time, I I
have to be honest, when I heard Bad, I
was a little bit like, I don't know if
I'm feeling him doing that. Um, when I
first heard bad, but what made me change
my mind was the video.
>> I still think it's up there as one of
his best. And it's also historically
interesting in his career. It marks the
final time he worked with Quincy Jones.
>> And Quincy got out before the
personality problems begin. Michael had
13 number ones in America as a solo
artist
and four with the Jackson five
and a lot of those number ones came off
the Bad album. Michael Jackson was
really at the point where he could call
the shots. He was already the number one
star in the world. The Bad World Tour
had kicked in. The singles were hit
records. His music was all over radio
stations worldwide. Bad was the number
one selling album of that year. But of
course he wanted to take his career to a
whole new area and go to the next level
which he did by starring and producing
this movie walker. Now it was never
going to win awards. It was never going
to win Oscars. But what it did do is
showcase the singles from Bad and give
him an opportunity to create the iconic
and incredible video that was Smooth
Criminal.
When you look at the very sleeve of
Dangerous,
you know we're into some choppy waters
here.
>> It was a big critical and commercial
disappointment, which is quite shocking
when you look back and think of all of
the huge tracks that came off that
album. Most notably, of course, Black or
White, which was the first single, a
mega tune.
Obviously, the fascination at that point
was about what Michael was trying to say
with that song. Black and White uh was
a big number one in America. Seven weeks
the video was big news starring McCauley
Kulkin as well.
>> Eat this.
What people often forget with the with
the black or white video is that it was
Michael's most controversial video and
it was censored. You have this main part
of it that most people are familiar
with, you know, where it's kind of a
celebration of diversity, you know, and
it's asking for tolerance and and just
kind of this this message that everyone
can kind of digest very easily. But what
happens after the end of the kind of the
main music video is a black panther kind
of sneaks off of the stage and then
Michael's conveying kind of the darker
side of of the song uh and of racism.
This was the period when the world was
shocked when Michael Jackson literally
did go within a few years from black to
white.
>> Everybody was starting to question,
okay, what's going on with the skin
color? Do you know this is really odd. I
personally believe that
no one quite knew if he was actually
trying to be white, but they all assumed
he was trying to make himself white. And
I think it angered a lot of people
because people felt he was such a
good-looking guy and gorgeous. A lot of
us were like upset that he was changing
his face. We're like, "Don't judge your
face, Michael. We love you the way you
are." Now, this was something that he
always put down to an illness, some sort
of rare disease.
There was a lot of doubts about that
throughout his life. Where was where was
the proof of this? And actually many
people thought that Michael Jackson over
a period of time had been bleaching his
skin. So this was a real statement for
him because he was essentially
responding to those criticisms through
song and saying, "Why does it matter if
I'm black or white?" The question back
to him obviously was, "Well, if it
doesn't matter, why have you potentially
done something to change the color of
your skin?" I mean, it really was, I
think, the beginning of a real terminal
decline for Michael in terms of how he
was viewed by the public.
>> Jackson was highly sensitive and
impressionable, and some of the public
and most of the media began to turn on
him due to his outlandish behavior, such
as purchasing a chimpanzee who he named
Bubbles and building a giant fun fair to
live in, Neverland.
In 1988, Michael Jackson set up, built,
and conceived, I guess, Neverland, which
is obviously the place where he would go
on to live for most the rest of his
life. It was also, I think, the moment
when the world became fascinated with
Michael Jackson's personal life. I mean,
here was a growing man at the peak of
his success who felt the need to live in
a huge amusement park. You're talking
about a young man who first became
successful with with his music at five.
So, you can imagine his whole life up to
that point was about being directed,
told what to do, and not really being
allowed to find who he was cuz he was
public property from such a young age.
So I think Neverland was his creation to
have a safe haven away from all of that
and also to finally express how he would
like to live his life for the first time
without anyone getting in the way. When
he first built this park in 1988, it
should be said it wasn't viewed as
something that was necessarily overtly
negative. It was more a fascination in
him. As the years went on, I think
Neverland became something that most
members of the public and most people in
the industry thought was pretty
unhealthy and and pretty odd.
Jackson was having a difficult time with
the media who often focused on his
unusual tendencies rather than his
immense generosity. He regularly gave
vast sums of money to charities and
worked extensively with terminally ill
and underprivileged children who he
invited to enjoy the wonders of
Neverland.
It was at this time that his fascination
with children became apparent as he even
took several children on tour with him
and proposed to adopt a boy and a girl
from every continent at one point. Heal
the Kids is about doing something about
making a difference and trying to help
adults and parents realize that it is
our power to change the world that our
children live in.
>> He suffered a horrendous accident whilst
on stage where his hair was set on fire
which resulted in secondderee burns, the
need for more plastic surgery, and the
start of his drug addiction.
when he burnt his hair at the Pepsi
commercial. He started using
painkillers. Then he then fell from a
stage and broke his leg. He also cracked
a vertebrae in his back and those things
have caused him terrible pain.
He wasn't well. You know, he had some
serious illnesses. you know, the
vitiligo, he had the burns from the
Pepsi ad and so he had a lot of plastic
surgery to reform, you know, parts of
his, you know, head and stuff like that.
I mean, there was a lot of there was a
lot of stuff that was hidden.
>> If you're going to understand why
Michael Jackson would have plastic
surgery, you've got to understand that
he was a human being, not a god-like
figure, and he was subject to the
insecurities that we all have.
Unfortunately, when he was really young,
he suffered a lot of abuse, you know,
from his father. His father called him
big nose.
>> So, he had,
he says, too, other people say more
rhinoplastes, that charming term given
to nose surgery. And then also, Michael
admitted to having the creation of a
dimple in his chin to look cute. But
what he never admitted to was lightening
his skin color. I think everyone was
very very concerned. We everyone was
just going, "What's going on with
Michael? Why is he changing the color of
his skin?" And everyone was starting to
think he didn't like being black
anymore.
>> When his skin began lightning, people
didn't know what to make of it. And then
finally, he told people that he had
vitiligo and people didn't believe him.
>> We didn't understand it cuz for us, he
was drop dead gorgeous. You know, we
were just obsessed with him. So, it was
a very confusing time for the fans. For
a long period of his career, people
didn't even know that he had vitiligo. I
think the first time that he mentioned
it publicly was to Oprah Winfrey, uh,
which was 1993.
>> I have a skin disorder that destroys the
pigmentation of the skin is something
that I cannot help. Okay. But when
people make up stories that I don't want
to be who I am, it hurts me. Imagine
being somebody that grows up in front of
the world and you have this pretty
unusual skin condition and people are
saying things like you are ashamed of
your race, you know, and you don't want
to be black. You're trying to be white.
So, there were things that he that were
his choice. I mean, the plastic
surgeries were certainly his choice, but
there were things that weren't his
choice. And the skin disorder was not
his choice, and it was something that he
had to deal with in front of the world.
He becomes uh to some people
a source of almost godlike virtue and
wisdom, to other people a figure of fun.
By the '90s, celebrity life was
destroying Michael. The media depicted
him as wacko Jacko. It was in 1993 that
things really took a turn for Michael,
who was accused of child molestation by
one of the children he was closest to.
The 1993 allegations was extremely
traumatic for Michael.
>> How everything started to go wrong with
Michael Jackson was with the child abuse
allegations.
>> I think for the first time people really
started to think, what is wrong with
Michael Jackson?
>> You're thinking, is it true? Isn't it
true? And this was always the general
consensus from people that you spoke to
was, I'm not sure. And you'd have some
people go, I think he did. It's typical.
It was this witch hunt. you know,
Michael and, you know, people that that
felt like they knew Michael always felt
like he was being tried by the media
because he was different, you know,
because he was unusual, because people
didn't know what to make sense of him.
So, of course, he must be a pedophile.
I don't believe that Michael Jackson
ever had
serious
full sex with a child because that would
be inconsistent with his self-image. To
take an adult role in sex, you have to
think of yourself as an adult
and he was trying to think of himself as
a child. I think if he had performed
overt sex with a child, he would be so
horrified he couldn't live with himself.
There was rumored that money did was
exchanged that the family of Jordan
Charlo were paid $20 million. This was
what was a a big mistake I believe on
Michael's part because I think not not
not that it was his mistake, his lawyers
advised them to do that, but I think
that this made the general public
question if it was true or not.
>> Do you think a father would accept
money? That that would make it okay?
that that would make everything all
right. It doesn't make any sense.
>> He in his own words described as a
humiliating experience. They did a strip
search on him, you know, took
photographs of him. They had like 70
police officers go through his property.
And what made him angry about it is that
they never found anything that would
indicate that he was in fact um guilty.
There are two relevant facts about
Michael Jackson and
the subject of pedophilia. One is he did
settle a court case with Jordie Chandler
for over $20 million.
The other is he was never convicted of
any criminal offense.
We have concluded that because the young
boy who is who is the catalyst
for this investigation has recently
informed us that he does not wish to
participate in any criminal proceeding
where he is named as a victim that we
must decline prosecution
involving Mr. Jackson
>> was his lifestyle rather than his music.
That was the thing that that the
majority of people outside of his
diehard fans would tend to focus on.
>> Michael was coming under so much
scrutiny that he often needed someone
who he could trust to share his life
with. And in this case, it happened to
be none other than Lisa Marie Presley,
of whom he started a relationship with
around the time of the allegations.
>> So, you're Michael Jackson and you know
how to make headlines. He does it again
in 94 when the king of pop marries the
daughter of the king of rock and roll.
It was also during the troubles and the
allegations that Michael faced during
the Jordan Chandler uh investigation in
93 that apparently he reached out to
Lisa Marie Presley and she was the
confidant. She was the person that spoke
to him on the phone and at the time of
course you have to remember he was also
battling painkiller and drug medication
addiction. All of a sudden, people were
very, very concerned about the way that
he looked. He was incredibly gaunt,
incredibly white, looked incredibly
surgically enhanced, and not in a good
way. Nobody saw this coming. Here was
the biggest music star of the last
decade, undisputedly, marrying the
daughter of the biggest music star of
all time, Elvis Presley. I mean, it was
completely fascinating. And I think to
this day, no one really knows what the
situation was between Michael Jackson
and Lisa Marie Prisy.
>> I thought this is really unusual. How
did that come about as well? But then we
all know that Michael did things that
was just unusual. It was always unusual.
But the two of them getting together,
this was very, very strange indeed. I
think everyone was like, "How did that
happen?"
>> And so they pretended for a while that
it could work. Maybe they even believed
it could work. Maybe they were so happy
that I've met a peer,
but they obviously were incompatible
because the marriage was shortlived.
>> I think after there was so much
intrusion and there was so much media
coverage of the tabloids went nuts and
and didn't believe it was real and I
guess it must have impacted the
relationship somehow. So, I don't think
the world was that surprised when
Michael Jackson's marriage to Lisa Marie
Presley ended in divorce.
>> After his and Lisa Marie's divorce,
Michael decided he wanted to have
children as soon as possible. This is
where Deborah Row came to the rescue.
>> She was quite a plain looking woman. She
was incredibly nononsense
and they had been friends, but I don't
think anyone really believed that there
was any form of sexual chemistry or
connection between the two of them. For
reasons that haven't ever become totally
clear, Michael decided to to marry her.
Michael had wanted kids for a long time.
In fact, he wanted kids with Lisa Marie
Presley, uh, which is one of the reasons
why they got a divorce. She was a
surrogate mother that provided him two
children. She's the woman that gave
birth to Prince Michael and his
daughter, Catherine. Friends, I wish for
you um to learn about perseverance and
confidence and the true meaning of
success, which is love, and to know that
you can reach any goal that your hearts
desire.
>> Daddy,
>> yeah,
>> I have Thank you for giving me ice
cream. You're the best daddy in the
whole world, and I love you,
>> Daddy. Thank you for my birthday cake
and and I I love you so much and and and
I I I
love my daddy so much.
>> By the end of their marriage, which was
very problematic and very troubled, it
became very clear that Michael had
viewed Debbie as the carrier of his
children really. And in the end, she
basically signed away her rights to
those children.
>> The press really did give Michael a
tough time about being a father.
However, when he finally released some
home footage of him with his children,
when we finally got to see footage of
him at home with the family at
Neverland, I think that it was obvious
to all of us what a doting uh and
perfect father he was. Uh just look at
that moment where he was celebrating, I
think, with Prince, his elder son. He'd
laid out some sort of puzzle on the
floor. He calls Prince over. He sits
down with his daddy. He starts playing
with the puzzle. Michael starts singing.
And it's so obvious that there was a
father and son who adored each other.
>> In 2002, Jackson has a third child,
Prince Michael, also known as Blanket,
whose biological mother was never
revealed,
>> but he claimed it been a result of
artificial insemination from a surrogate
mother and his own sperm cells. Blankie
himself became front page news and a
star in his own right when Michael
dangled him. He held on to him, but he
dangled him over a balcony in a hotel in
Germany to hundreds of his fans who were
downstairs uh on the ground crying out
for him to show his new son. Again, you
have to ask, okay, why did he do that?
Because he did it voluntarily. Nobody
was holding a gun on him, saying, "Hold
your child out at a great height." And
he was so carried away with the
excitement and happiness and also
proving look I'm a man I have a child
and for that moment he forgot the
interest of the child. It was a moment
as well that was featured in the Michael
Jackson Martin Bashier documentary but
at the time he defended despite so many
people criticizing what he exactly what
he did including child protection
charities. Michael was determined to
argue his case saying I'm a fantastic
dad. I was holding on tight. I got
caught up in the moment, but my child
was never at risk.
>> It happens for like two seconds, but
when it gets on the news, they slow it
down. They don't show the crowd and
making like I'm just a century idiot
dangling his baby over the balcony like
a nut.
In 1995,
2 years after the child abuse
allegations, the world was yet again
waiting for a new Michael Jackson
record.
An album that would ultimately make or
break him.
>> The release of history did not go down
well. It was a greatest hits package
combined with a new album. And there are
a whole load of stunts which were really
derided. For example, Michael Jackson
deciding to send a massive statue of
himself down the rivers in London
despite him being still caught up in all
of these allegations of child abuse. And
I was on breakfast television that day
and people were talking about this and
raving about it. And I said, uh, I don't
want to spoil the party, but I'm the
only one here who isn't thrilled by this
because, uh, this really, uh, indicates
a loss of perspective. The record itself
goes to number one in the UK and around
Europe, uh, including Germany. It stayed
at number one for weeks on end. In fact,
it was the Christmas number one of 1995.
The album history was back into the into
the top five because of this record. And
actually, I always felt like history was
probably his most underrated album ever.
I mean, some of the songs to come from
history are completely iconic. They
don't really care about us. Earth Song.
With Earth Song, there's a demo that was
going to go on the Dangerous album, but
Michael was such a perfectionist that he
just wasn't quite satisfied with it. So
when he came back and did it again, he
has these really gritty, this kind of
gritty shout, you know, that he's doing
against, you know, the choir would come
in, you know, what about us? And then he
would come in, you know, with this kind
of shout instead of the cry, the
falsetto cry. So there's just these kind
of subtle changes that that would take
place that, you know, in in a lot of
cases made the song better, but it took
years
You know, the Earth song video really
was something quite powerful. It had
quite an impact. I mean, Michael didn't
pull any punches with this video. And of
course, the last two minutes of the
video show the Earth being reversed back
to goodness. Trees going back up and the
sun shining and ultimately Michael
Jackson looking like the savior.
So then the second single came along and
it was You Are Not Alone and it was a
real Michael Jackson ballad in the true
sense of the word and it did become a
huge hit for him. I guess really against
all odds because the music video was
incredibly strange. I mean, it featured
Michael Jackson almost naked under the
sheets with his wife, Lisa Marie
Presley, and it was a very odd music
video.
>> And this is the moment that sends the
history album racing up to number one
and went on to sell over 20 million
copies worldwide.
After mixed reviews of history, Michael
then released Invincible in 2001, an
album that took over three years to be
created.
I think it's fair to say that in terms
of Michael Jackson's career, Invincible,
his 2001 studio album, wasn't his finest
hour. Critics accused Michael of
borrowing from old ideas. It was too
much like Smooth Criminal, a bit like
The Way You Make Me Feel. Michael was
accused of being a bit tired and jaded.
However, he also suffered as the album
release tied in within weeks of the
madness and the tragedy of 9/11 in New
York. And at the time when he was meant
to be promoting the album, Invincible,
Michael took some of the biggest names
in music into a studio to record a
charity single called What More Can I
Give? Sony refused to release that
single. And from that moment, the
promotion of Invincible suffered. And in
fact, within six months, Sony had
decided to stop promoting altogether.
In 2003, Jackson is again charged with
sexual abuse and administering
intoxicating agents to Gavin Arzo, a
close child friend of Michael's, who was
under 14 at the time of the alleged
crime.
>> The service of the warrants was part of
an ongoing investigation alleging
criminal misconduct on the part of
Michael Jackson.
The basis for this investigation
regarding Mr. Jackson involves
allegations of child molestation
288a of the California Penal Code.
>> Then we have this surreal moment where
the biggest selling artist of all time,
one of the biggest stars in the world,
is captured live on 24 news channels,
handcuffed walking into a police
station.
This was his worst nightmare. He was
pretty clear to those around him that he
thought a trial of this kind would kill
him.
>> The trial dragged on for months and it
really wore him out.
>> He was emphatic that he was an innocent
man. His family came out in support of
him. Some of the biggest names in music
said, "How can you accuse Michael
Jackson once again of such a heinous
crime?
>> I don't believe any of this stuff that's
being written about him cuz I raised him
and I know I mean that's just a
statement people are making. We support
our brother wholeheartedly and um um we
stand by by his side and there is we're
in the process of planning a trip with
the whole family to to visit him.
>> The world felt for the first time at
least the world of the media that
actually maybe these years and years and
years of of managing to get around the
law, however he had done that, had
finally caught up with Michael. Please
keep an open mind and let me have my day
in court. I deserve a fair trial like
every other American citizen. I will be
acquitted and vindicated when the truth
is told.
>> So much of the attention on Michael
Jackson through that whole 6-month
trial, which was just, you know,
wallto-wall coverage was on his
eccentricities,
scandals, all these different things.
And I thought, you know, what's getting
lost here is that Michael Jackson is an
incredible artist.
>> Michael Jackson's career in America was
effectively ended by the allegations of
child abuse.
So, after being found not guilty on all
counts in 2005, after the media had
essentially put Michael Jackson through
one trial and of course the court
process the other, Michael had gone away
to work on new music to bring up his
three children and we had waited and
wondered would he ever return to the
stage. The announcement of the This Is
It tour, which had been backed by AEG,
was very significant. Money was a huge
factor for Michael Jackson over his
final years. He was broke. He had lived
well beyond his means. So the idea
behind these farewell concerts that he
was very passionate about was not only
that he could go out in the way that he
wanted to on stage, but also that he'd
make the millions and millions of
dollars which he desperately needed.
>> This is it. I mean, this is really it.
This is the final This is the final
curtain call.
The idea of a limited series of shows at
the O2 in London had grown to an
extended season.
>> All of a sudden, there were 40 dates and
then potentially there were going to be
more and it was going to be a residency
which could last well over a year.
>> Everyone wanted to believe that he was
he was the eternal Peter Pan. Then he
started rehearsing and there were very
very concerning reports to come out of
these rehearsals from quite early on.
Really reports that Michael simply
wasn't turning up to the rehearsals.
Reports that really just months out from
the start of these career definfining
concerts, Michael hadn't even been able
to perform a few songs in a row.
Get me out. Bam. Something right there.
is just an apple.
>> I always thought that Michael would be
tempted to take refuge in some form of
seditive.
>> Because clearly to anybody,
>> just thinking about it, it's an
extraordinarily worrying prospect.
>> I've got to go out there for over 50
nights.
and do this incredible workout.
>> July 2009 was going to be the moment
that Michael finally returned to the
stage and proved why he had the title
the king of pop. And of course, as we
now know, it was never meant to be.
>> Fire paramedic 33, what is your
emergency?
>> Yes, sir. I need to I uh I need an
ambulance as soon as possible, sir.
>> Okay, sir. What's your address? It's 100
North Carolwood Drive, Los Angeles,
California 90077.
You
>> said Carolwood.
>> Carolwood Drive. Yes.
>> Yes.
>> On June 25th, 2009,
Los Angeles Fire Department responded to
the 100 block of Carolwood at 1221 and
18 seconds. Unfortunately, at the time,
the dispatcher answered the phone call
and and never once did the caller ever
identify to the Los Angeles Fire
Department that the person that needed
our help was Michael Jackson.
>> He's not responding to anything to know.
No, he's not responding to the CPR or
anything, sir.
>> Oh, okay. Well, we're on our way there.
If you're doing CPR and you're
instructed by doctor, he has a higher
authority than me.
>> The question is, why did it take Dr.
Murray so long to dial 911? Only Dr.
Murray can answer that question.
Obviously, fast response saved lives.
Why Dr. Murray took so long and whoever
long he noticed that Michael Jackson was
down, it's unexplainable to us.
I had thought that for the past 15
years, Michael had obviously been on a
downward trajectory
in terms of his relationship with
reality and his perception of himself.
What I couldn't know, of course, and
which nobody knew was the extent to
which he was taking prescription drugs.
And there's only so much the body can
take. I thought Michael Jackson would
not go into the hospital voluntarily.
He'd have the hospital come to him.
This is really serious.
I still can't believe it. I mean, he's
like the last of one of I think God's
gifts of innocent, loving person that
cared truly about everybody. And there's
nobody else like him.
>> THIS MAN BROUGHT US TOGETHER, BABY. WE
LOVE MICHAEL JACKSON.
I think it was the incredibly powerful
and emotional moment that Paris Jackson
spoke at her father's memorial in July
2009 in Los Angeles where she through
sobs of tears told the world how much
she missed her dad what a great daddy
Michael had been. I think that was the
turning point where the media decided to
actually celebrate the fact that Michael
had been a fantastic father to three
children.
Ever since I was born,
Daddy has been the best father you could
ever imagine.
The Jackson family were subject to more
heartbreak when in February 2010, the
cause of Jackson's death was released.
>> How do you plead?
>> Your honor, I am an innocent man. I
therefore plead not guilty.
>> Thank you.
>> I think Dr. Conrad Murray was part
of why Michael Jackson died. I know that
allowing a patient to take this drug off
hospital site
is extraordinarily unwise
and to do so on a
occasional or frequent basis is to
invite death. Michael had problems and
he you know he felt a lot of pressure
and there was a lot of money involved
and certainly Michael made choices but
at the same time there's this doctor
that had an ethical responsibility even
when he's giving him this propul to
monitor him to not leave the room
>> it was gross neglect you know and this
this was not
someone that I would
trust as my doctor
>> there's a lot of negligent doctors out
there who've done horrendous things and
they're still practicing medicine. Their
patient wasn't Michael Jackson.
>> Dr. Conrad Murray knew what he was
doing. He knew that things that were
being asked of him weren't ethical. He
made his choices and and he has to live
with the with the repercussions.
>> You have to remember for some people
it's difficult to say no to a superstar.
If Michael Jackson wants something,
I've got to give it to him because
otherwise I won't be his doctor anymore.
>> I think the guilty verdict for Dr.
Conrad Murray was not a surprise in a
lot of ways because yes, he had helped
Michael Jackson get this huge quantity
of procol which was the drug which in
the end did help lead to his demise. I
do have a feeling, however, that Michael
Jackson was going to get his hands on
these legal drugs in any way he possibly
could. He was addicted.
>> Jackson often said he felt like the
loneliest person in the world. And in
1982, he narrated the story book of ET,
the extraterrestrial,
another outsider from children's fiction
he identified with like Peter Pan.
He often said, "ET's story is the story
of my life in so many ways." However,
unlike ET, Jackson never found a true
home except on stage, which was, he said
in 1979, "Where I'm supposed to be,
where God meant me to be."
If ever there was an illustration of the
fact that celebrity destroys what it
touches, Jackson was it. But we remember
the king of pop not for what others said
about him but what we heard in his music
and saw in his performances.
The most influential and multi-talented
artist of all time.
When you talk about Michael Jackson's
legacy I mean wow we could talk all day
about his contribution. I mean it's that
significant a complete gamecher. When we
talk about influence, it's there in the
videos, in choreography, in style, in
playing the media, in promotion, and in
songwriting. Michael Jackson's work
resonated for people because of the soul
that Michael put into it and people
could feel that there was something
genuine. There was something that just
radiated life in his work. So, we all
know that Michael was the ultimate
performer, one of the greatest showmans
of all time. But he was also a
perfectionist and he never ever stopped
recording writing songs. I mean, that's
what he did whenever he had spare time.
He was constantly writing lyrics. He was
constantly in the studio. He wanted
perfection. He wanted to find the next
hit record. So, after Michael passed in
2009, a whole new generation of fans
were downloading and buying into Michael
Jackson's music like never before. I
think you saw when when Michael Jackson
died uh something that maybe certain
people didn't expect which is that there
was this huge outpouring
across the world. He is the greatest
selling artist of all time. He's
influenced a generation of artists be it
Beyonce, Justin Timberlake, Bieber,
Rihanna, some of the biggest names in
music today. Whenever I interview these
stars, they all talk about one man. They
talk about Michael Jackson.
>> Michael's work was able to cross
divisions. uh and and reach people all
over the world.
>> He changed the face of music, the sound
of music and the industry and the world
is a lesser place without him.